站起来
On your feet!
《夺宝奇兵5：命运转盘》
是美国人 上校
An American, Colonel.
他在大门假装是军官
He was at the gate, impersonating an officer.
你一个人
You were alone?
间谍 你一个人
Spy, you were alone?
我喜欢一个人
I like to be alone.
你来做什么
What did you come here for?
你们有不少好东西
You got a lot of nice stuff.
别人的东西
Other people's stuff.
赢家通吃
"To the victor belongs the spoils."
赢家
"To the victor"?
柏林已成废墟
Berlin's in rubble.
纳粹元首躲起来
The Führer's in hiding.
你们输了
You lost.
带他到楼上
Take him upstairs.
什么
What? What?
喂
Hey!
等一下
Hey, wait a second. Guys!
请等一下
A moment. Please!
停 我得跟指挥官谈
Stop! I must speak to the commander.
上校 我找到了
Colonel. I found it!
听他的 打开
Do as he says. Open it.
朗基努斯之枪
The Lance of Long in us.
沾染基督之血的长矛
The blade that drew Christ's blood.
圣枪
The Holy Lance.
加强维安 这是元首在找的宝物
Double the guard. This is the prize the Führer seeks.
上校 我们谈一下
Colonel, we need to talk.
没空 博士
No time, Doctor.
往柏林的火车在等你
The train to Berlin is waiting.
搜索树林
Search the woods!
带狗去
Take the dogs.
你们想那间谍是一个人吗
Do you think that spy was alone?
快…出发
Go! Go! Go! We're moving out!
动作快
On the double!
看来他们丢下你们了
Looks like they're leaving without you guys.
说说你的来历 否则没命
Tell us your story, or die.
来历
Story.
好…
Okay, okay.
哦
Well…
一开始
it all started…
在很久很久以前 有个村子
once upon a time, when this village…
一群愚蠢的蓝眼男孩决定一起加入
of stupid blue-eyed boys decided to join hands together…
追随名叫阿道夫的吹笛手
and follow this sweaty little pied piper named Adolf…
（美国炸弹）
不
No.
这个人跟那美国佬一伙的
This man was with the American.
这是美国背包
This is the American's bag.
我做了什么
What have I done?
带他到我的车厢
Bring him to my carriage.
小心 这是元首的特殊文物
Careful. This is the Führer's special relic!
坐好
Stay seated.
所以…
So…
你是赏鸟人
you are a birdwatcher?
是 因为轰炸的关系
Yes. Because of the bombing,
鹡鸰的飞行路线完全改变
the wagtails are following a completely different trajectory.
我们抓到你的同伙
We caught your accomplice.
那个美国佬
The American.
完了
Oh, my!
放开我
Get off of me!
你还活着是有原因的 赏鸟人
There's one reason you're still alive, birdwatcher.
谁派你来的
Who sent you?
有什么任务
What was your mission?
拜托 上校 我求你
Please, Colonel, no. I beg you.
我叫贝索萧
My name is Basil Shaw.
我是牛津大学教授
I'm a professor at Oxford.
考古学家
An archeologist.
找到了
There you are.
有个问题
There is a problem.
我有话跟上校说
I must speak to the Colonel.
是急事
It's urgent.
我有女儿 我求你
I have a daughter. I beg you.
我保证你再也见不到孩子 萧先生
I guarantee you will never see your child again, Mr. Shaw.
除非你说明你的同伙怎么有这个
Unless you explain why your accomplice had this.
我们听说能在堡垒找到朗基努斯之枪
We were told that the Lance of Long in us could be found at the fortress.
我们在找它
We were looking for it.
为什么
Why?
因为它的魔力
Because of its power?
它没有魔力
It has no power.
我和我朋友想抢救历史文物
My friend and I were trying to save history.
我必须跟上校谈
I must speak with the Colonel.
跟圣枪有关
It's about the Lance.
我只看了一下子
I only had a moment to look at it.
当然 我的专长是物理
Of course, my training is in physics,
老天 有屁快放
For God's sake, spit it out!
那把圣枪…
The Lance…
冒牌货
It's a fake.
是冒牌货
冒牌货
A fake?
枪头是合金
The blade is an alloy.
只有50年历史
Fifty years old,
雕刻是新的 它是复制品
the engravings recent. It's a replica.
我们死定了
We're dead.
12世纪 13世纪
Twelfth century. Thirteenth century.
拉美西斯二世
Ramesses II.
这些都不是假的
None of this stuff is fake.
我得拦下这列火车
I gotta stop this train.
火车上还有另一件文物
There is another relic on this train.
拥有真正的魔力
One with real power.
你在说什么
What are you talking about?
安提基瑟拉仪
The Antikythera.
The Antikythera?!
别再讲那个老轮盘了
Enough about that old dial!
上校 元首输掉战争
Colonel, the Führer has lost the war…
也失心疯了
and his mind!
容我说明
Let me explain.
安提基瑟拉仪的力量不在超自然
The Antikythera's power is not supernatural.
而是数学
It is mathematics.
能驾驭它的人
Whoever harnesses it…
不会成为国王
will not be King…
也不是皇帝
nor Emperor…
或元首
or Führer.
他会成为上帝
He will be God.
太多纳粹了
Too many Nazis.
你建议我们该怎么跟他说
And how do you propose we tell him this?
我的元首
My Führer,
很遗憾圣枪是假的
I'm sorry the Lance of Christ is fake.
不过您看
But here is…
这个缺一半的东西是您没听过的
half of something you've never heard of.
告诉我
Tell me,
你见过希特勒吗
have you ever met Hitler?!!
车上有破坏分子
A saboteur aboard.
希特勒的圣枪不见了
And Hitler's Lance is gone.
那边
That way!
你在这里干嘛
What are you doing here?!
怎么搞的
What the hell?
印第
Indy?
老贝
Baz?
你还活着
You're alive!
目前是
So far.
我不是叫你待在树林里吗
I thought I told you to stay in the woods, Baz.
朋友生死交关 怎么能躲在树篱里
What sort of a man hides in a hedge while his friend is facing death?
这些人掠夺世界半数古董
This lot are carting off half the world's antiquities.
我想阻止他们 但现在得先救你
I was gonna stop 'em, but now I've gotta rescue you.
你至少找到圣枪了吧
Did you at least find the Lance?
- 至少 - 找到了吗
- "At least"? - Well, have you got it?
它是假的
It's a fake.
什么
What?
复制品
A reproduction.
你是谁
Who are you?
印第
Indy?
安提基瑟拉仪
The Antikythera.
阿基米德的轮盘
Archimedes' Dial.
带走
Bring it.
快点 老贝
Hurry up, Baz.
给我
Give me that.
快走
Come on.
起来 老贝
Get up, Baz.
跟我来
Follow me.
走向枪林弹雨
Towards the gun?
远离纳粹
Away from the Nazis!
那些人就是纳粹
Those are Nazis!
趴下…
Get down! Down! Down!
走这边 快
This way. Come on!
我没办法
I can't do that!
你想躺下来休息吗
You wanna stop for a little lie-down?
他们拿走安提基瑟拉仪了
They have the Antikythera!
小心
Easy.
隧道
Tunnel!
抓住你了 不
Got you! No!
印第
Indy!
拿枪
Get the gun!
射他
Shoot him!
不是射我
Not me!
抱歉
Sorry.
赢家通吃
To the victor go the spoils.
把枪放下
Drop the gun.
安提基瑟拉仪给我
Give me the Antikythera.
印第
Indy!
喂
Hey!
- 这边 - 他们听不见 老贝
- Here! - They can't hear you, Baz.
我们得跳车
We gotta jump!
我膝盖不好怎么办
What about my dicky knee?
老贝
Baz!
- 印第 - 老贝
- Indy! - Baz!
走 快走
Go! Move! Move it!
两手空空回家有点糗
Bit rum to go home empty-handed after all that.
两手空空
"Empty-handed"?
怎么会
Not exactly.
阿基米德的轮盘
Archimedes' Dial.
只有一半
Well, half of it.
走吧 老贝 我们回家去
Come on, Baz. Let's get home.
赖瑞 小声点
Larry! Turn it down!
小声一点
Turn it down!
喂 赖瑞
Hey, Larry!
赖瑞
Larry!
- 琼斯先生 - 赖瑞呢
- Hi, Mr. Jones. - Where's Larry?
这家伙是谁
Who is this guy?
隔壁的老头
It's the old guy next door.
赖瑞 现在早上8点
Larry, it's 8:00 in the morning.
- 现在早上8点 - 我们讲过了
- "It's 8:00 in the morning." - We talked about this, Larry.
对 不过那是…
Yeah, but that was…
- 平日 - 今天也是平日 赖瑞
- a workday, Mr. Jones. - This is a workday too, Larry!
看一下新闻
Turn on the news.
今天登月日 琼斯先生
It's moon day, Mr. Jones.
登月日
Moon day?
（玛莉安·瑞文伍 小亨利·华顿·琼斯 无异议分居）
谢谢
Thanks.
你们只要记住
All you really need to remember…
这时期的亚述陶器…
is that Assyrian ceramics of this period are characterized…
都有复杂的蓝线图案
by this complex blue-line pattern.
懂吗
Okay?
我指定你们今天要看温福的书
I assigned pages 131 through 171…
第131到171页
in Winford for today.
有人看了吗
Anybody do the reading?
有吗
Anyone?
这个会考哦
Gosh, this is on the test.
好吧
Okay.
那我直接讲给你们听
Guess I'll spoon-feed it to you.
公元前213年
In 213 BC…
马塞卢斯率领罗马军队
Roman forces led by Marcellus…
包围叙拉古城
laid siege to the city of Syracuse.
叙拉古耶
"Syracuse."
不是纽约州的那个 谭雅
Not the Syracuse in New York, Tonya.
在西西里
The one in Sicily.
在捍卫这座城市的人当中
Amongst the defenders of the city…
有一个知名的居民 他是…
was its most famous resident, who was…
快点 期末考会考
Come on, guys. This is on the final.
阿基米德
Archimedes.
阿基米德 他是…
Archimedes, who was a…
数学家
A mathematician.
除此之外 也是发明家
But more than that, an inventor…
杰出的工程师
a brilliant engineer…
他想办法将地中海的太阳能
who conceived of a way to harness the energy of the Mediterranean sun…
集中在凹面镜上
on concave mirrors and focus it…
借以攻击罗马战舰 使它们着火
on attacking Roman warships and set them on fire.
他设计出庞大的铁爪
Who devised giant iron claws…
在海上抓敌
that could snatch hostiles from the sea.
我们怎么知道那真的发生过
But how do we know it really happened?
这些发明有没有无可辩驳
What physical, irrefutable archeological evidence…
- 确切的考古证据 - 安提基瑟拉仪
- is there of these inventions? - The Antikythera.
- 安提基瑟拉仪 - 那只是开始
- The Antikythera. - For starters.
他们来了 在市区
They're here! They're downtown!
太空人
The astronauts.
早上将有250万人…
Giant parade this morning will be seen…
在人行道上观赏这场大游行
by about two and a half million people lining the sidewalks…
他来了
He's coming. He's come. See?
Oh, here he comes.
蛋糕藏起来
Hide the cake.
- 惊喜 - 惊喜
- Surprise. - Surprise!
十几年来
For over a decade now…
琼斯博士一直在亨特学院认真奉献
our colleague Dr. Jones has been a loyal servant of Hunter.
谨以这纪念品表达谢意
A token of our gratitude.
哇
Wow.
（退休快乐）
谢谢大家容忍我
Thanks for putting up with me.
送你
Here.
太空人阿姆斯壮 科林斯与艾德林
Astronauts Neil Armstrong, Mike Collins, and Buzz Aldrin…
将无法避开镁光灯
will not be able to avoid the spotlight.
东部夏令时间上午11点 为表敬意
At 11:00 a.m. Eastern Daylight Time, a grateful nation will pay homage…
纽约与芝加哥将举行纸带游行
with a ticker-tape parade through New York and Chicago…
高潮是洛杉矶的晚宴…
climaxed by a dinner in Los Angeles…
古人会怎么说
What would the ancients say?
尼尔 巴兹和麦克…
Neil, Buzz, and Mike…
如果他们知道我们登陆月球
If they knew we walked on the moon?
从我这个古人的角度来看
Speaking as an ancient…
上月球就像去赌城雷诺
going to the moon is like going to Reno.
鸟不生蛋
Middle of nowhere…
却没有21点可玩
and no blackjack.
你不认得我了吧
You don't recognize me, do you?
不管怎样 我道歉
Whatever I did, I apologize.
我是海伦娜
It's Helena.
海伦娜·萧
Helena Shaw.
袋熊
Wombat?
好久没人这样叫我了
Wow, I haven't heard that in a while.
- 你长高了 - 对啊
- You got tall. - I did.
没错
It's fair to say.
我在庆祝
I'm celebrating.
我要退休了
I'm retiring.
那该喝什么呢
Wow. Well, in that case, what are we drinking?
史密兹先生的客房服务
Room service for Mr. Schmidt.
收起来
Put that away.
我在问你脚踝怎么受伤的
I was asking how you broke your ankle.
不关你的事
None of your business.
您是史密兹先生吗
Are you Mr. Schmidt?
史密兹博士 他在里面
"Doctor" Schmidt. He's in there.
他不吃摆在轮子上的东西 放在桌上
And he don't eat anything on wheels, so put it on a table.
小时候
When I was a little boy…
我常梦想
I always imagined…
有一天人类能在月球上漫步
that one day man would walk on the moon.
天啊…
And by golly…
外面庆祝活动好热闹
Quite a celebration out there.
你服务的这个人
The man you're servin'…
就是他让太空人上月球的
he's the one who put those astronauts on the moon.
他建造他们搭的火箭
Built the rockets they rode in.
恭喜
Congratulations.
你哪里人
Where are you from?
布朗克斯 先生
The Bronx, sir.
不 我是说你祖先哪来的
No, no. I mean originally, your people.
你知道吗
Do you know?
我在洋基球场旁出生
I was born by Yankee Stadium, sir.
为国出征过吗
And you fought for your country?
第320营
320th Battalion.
用防空气球阻止战机轰炸诺曼底
Set up balloons to stop the planes bombing Normandy.
你喜欢你们的胜利吗
And are you enjoying your victory?
还有其他吩咐吗
Will there be anything else?
你们战争没打赢
You didn't win the war.
是希特勒输了
Hitler lost it.
是
Yeah.
我的探员 她发现了萧
My field agent, she found Shaw.
好 我来了
Yeah, I'm comin'.
走吧 华克
Let's go, Hauke.
这是在哪里
Where are we here?
牛津 花园里
Oxford. In the garden.
他独树一格
He was an original.
我刚毕业
I just graduated.
考古学
In Archeology.
考古学 哇
Archeology. Wow.
有其父必有其女
Apple didn't fall far.
我要攻读博士学位
Well, now I'm researching a doctorate.
研究什么主题
What's your subject?
阿基米德轮盘
The Archimedes Dial.
安提基瑟拉仪
The Antikythera.
你对它了解多少
What do you know about that?
首先
Well, for starters…
海绵潜水夫1902年在希腊外海
in 1902, Greek sponge divers found a wrecked Roman warship…
发现一艘罗马战舰 庞然大物
huge, off the coast of Greece.
用蜡密封起来的甲板底下
Below deck, sealed in wax…
有一台像时钟的机器
was a clock-like mechanism…
作工精细 用途不明
finely tooled, purpose unknown.
有千年没出现过复杂度能匹敌的装置
Nothing approximating its complexity appears in the world for 1, 000 years.
- 你有做功课哦 - 不是我
- You've done your homework. - Well, not me.
我爸有好多日志 大量笔记
Dad. He had all these journals, reams of notes about it.
他一生着迷不已
He was obsessed till the end.
他说你在纳粹的掠夺列车上发现它
He told me you found it on a Nazi plunder train.
然后掉在法国阿尔卑斯山的河里
And then lost it in a river in the French Alps.
那是很久以前的事
Well, that was a long time ago.
只是半个轮盘
And it was only half the Dial.
- 阿基米德… - 阿基米德拆成两半
- Archimedes… - Archimedes broke the Dial in two…
- 把它拆开 - 然后藏起来
- …disassembled it. - …and then hid…
以免叙拉古被包围时让罗马人发现
the two halves from the Romans during the siege of Syracuse.
我知道 你看
I know. Look.
你不记得上次我见到你吧
You don't remember the last time I saw you, do you?
记得什么
Remember what?
这是阿尔卑斯山
These are the Alps.
我知道
Yeah, I see.
这是你列车走的路线
And this is the route that your train took…
- 1944年从纳粹据点出发 - 对
- from the Nazi stronghold in '44. - Right.
它经过这个隘口
It went through this mountain pass…
然后到了这里
and then here.
- 这是途中唯一一条河 - 对
- Here, it's the only river on the route. - Right.
在一座桥下
Under a bridge.
它一定在那里
It's down there. It's got to be.
- 只有我们知道 - 我们
- And nobody knows except us. - "Us"?
我是说你
Well, I mean, you.
还有我 对
And me. So, yeah.
- 我们 - 我们
- Us. - Us.
你到底打什么主意
And what were you thinking exactly?
说不定…
Well, that maybe…
我们可以去那里
we could go there.
然后呢
And?
找到它
And find it.
那我就…
And I'd become…
出名了
famous.
不是出名
Oh, well, not famous.
声誉卓著 受尊敬
Renowned. Feted.
受尊敬的考古学家
A feted archeologist.
也是你最后的一大成就
And you, a final triumph!
印第安纳·琼斯
Indiana Jones!
大获成功 重出江湖
Out with a bang! Back in the saddle!
你不心动吗
I'm not selling this, am I?
袋熊
Wombat…
你为何要追求
why are you chasing the thing…
把你老爸逼疯的东西
that drove your father crazy?
你不会吗
Wouldn't you?
我自己来
I got it.
游行快开始了
Parade's comin' soon.
有什么发现
So, what we got?
她在里面 跟一个老头在三楼
She's in there, third floor, with an old guy.
他是谁 俄国人吗
Who is he, a Russian?
一个教授 亨利·琼斯博士
No, a professor. Dr. Henry Jones.
克雷柏
Klaber!
克雷柏 回来 你不是探员
Klaber, get back here! You're not an agent!
该死 快去
Goddammit! Go.
我来请求支援 调琼斯的档案
I'll get support up here and pull a file on Jones.
这边
This way.
贝索迷上了这个德国理论
Basil became obsessed by this German theory.
其实是猜测
Conjecture, really.
阿基米德发现
Archimedes had figured out…
月球和行星的运动
that the movements of the moon and planets…
并不完美
weren't perfect.
它们的自转呈现不规则
There were irregularities in their rotations.
他认为这些不规则或许…
He thought these irregularities might…
能解释温度和潮汐的变动
explain fluctuations in temperature, tides.
甚至风暴
Storms, even.
他打算建造一个预测装置
So, he set about building a device to predict them.
结果他发现一个方法能预测更大的…
But then, he stumbled upon a method to predict even larger…
扰动
disturbances.
更大的扰动
Larger disturbances?
你父亲认为这玩意能…
Your father thought this thing could…
预测时间的裂缝
predict fissures in time.
华克 如果你不…
Hauke, if you don't…
找到他们了
Found 'em.
你们好
Hello.
你们在找…
Are you looking for…
琼斯博士
Dr. Jones?
需要帮忙吗
Excuse me, can I help you?
不用 谢谢
No, thank you.
只是例行调查
Just a routine investigation, ma'am.
你们是警察吗
Are you the police?
一下子就好
It'll just be a few moments.
- 普林顿教授 - 小姐
- Professor Plimpton. - Ma'am.
- Professor Plimpton! - Ma'am!
武器放下
Drop your weapon.
你在干什么
What the hell are you doin'?
奉博士的指示行事 梅森小姐
What the doctor tells me, Miss Mason.
曼蒂
Mandy?
对 没有目击者
Yeah, no witnesses.
天啊 搞什么
Jesus. What the hell?
你父亲有好多信在谈轮盘 我没看完
Your father wrote so many letters about the Dial, I stopped reading 'em.
真的不记得我上次去你家
You really don't remember the last time I was at your house?
我当时跟他拿的
I took that from him then.
我以为他不再想它了
I thought he'd stopped thinking about it.
但你爸深信这玩意既真实又危险
But your father was convinced this thing was real and dangerous.
别开枪
Do not shoot.
他怕有人发现那块传奇的刻写板
He was terrified that if somebody found this legendary tablet,
格拉飞科
the Grafikos…
指引剩余轮盘下落的刻写板
The tablet containing directions to the rest of the Dial.
如果他们发现格拉飞科
And if they found the Grafikos…
就可能取得另一半轮盘
they might acquire the other half of the Dial…
将两者组合起来
and put the two together.
我就知道你不会摧毁它
I knew you wouldn't destroy it.
你怎么知道他要我摧毁它
How did you know he asked me to destroy it?
什么
What?
你果然记得那一夜
You do remember that night.
- 我才12岁 - 你知道它没掉进河里
- I was 12 years old, Indy. - You knew we didn't drop it in a river.
老贝没告诉你
Baz didn't tell you that.
- 听我说 我没… - 他从不撒谎
- See, listen. I didn't… - No, he never lied.
- 不 - 干嘛瞎掰地图的事
- No. You… - What was all that crap about the map?
你喝太多威士忌了
No, you've had too many whiskeys.
你想干嘛 袋熊
What are you doing, Wombat?
留在原地
Stay where you are.
不要动
Don't move.
- 这些人是谁 - 我们得快离开
- Who are these people? - We need to get out of here.
他们跟你一伙
Are they with you?
别动 萧小姐
Not an inch, Miss Shaw.
萧小姐 站住
Miss Shaw, stop!
海伦娜
Helena!
别跑
Stop!
对不起
Sorry.
海伦娜
Helena!
琼斯博士 结束了
Dr. Jones. It's over.
你们是谁
Who are you people?
你们想干嘛
What do you want?
别跑
Stop!
海伦娜·萧
Helena Shaw!
她在屋顶上 从别的地方上去
She's on the roof. Find another way up.
琼斯博士
Dr. Jones!
琼斯博士 我们不会伤害你
Dr. Jones, we're not gonna hurt you.
- 去追他们 - 快去
- Move. We gotta follow 'em. - Go. Hurry up.
分头追
Fan out!
快…带走
Let's go. Move, move, move! Pack it up!
全部搬走
Come on. Get everything.
找到她了
Found her!
- 总机 - 我要报警
- Operator. - I need the police.
亨特学院 有人死了
Hunter College. People are dead.
- 拜托… - 挂断
- Please… - Hang up, fella.
起来
Stand up.
好啦
Okay, okay.
她溜了 你搞砸了
She's gone. You blew it…
乱开枪的小白脸
you trigger-happy cracker.
- 东西在她手上 - 逮到教授了
- She had it in her hand. - We got the professor.
琼斯的档案
Here's the file on Jones.
很好
Yes.
你们是谁
Who are you?
我才要问你呢
That's my question.
你们是中情局的
You're CIA.
我不是
Oh, not me, man.
我不接政府的案子
I don't take government jobs.
好
Okay.
你怎么认识萧小姐
How are you acquainted with Miss Shaw?
她是我的干女儿
She's my goddaughter.
我有18年没见到她了
I haven't seen her in 18 years.
今天为何跟她见面 给她轮盘吗
Why did you meet with her today? To give her the Dial?
小姐 那是笨重的老古董
Lady, it's an ancient hunk of gears.
半个古董
Half a hunk.
不只如此
Oh, it's a lot more than that.
喂…
Whoa, whoa, whoa!
你想去哪
Where do you think you're going?
这里在游行
I got a parade going on.
有抗议队伍要过来
And a demonstration coming down here.
喂…
Hey! Hey, hey!
- 喂… - 闭嘴
- Hey… - Shut up.
这边不能走 我得倒车
I can't go this way. Gotta go back.
干嘛 你有毛病啊
Hell no! What is wrong with you, man?
可恶 我们用走的
Damn it! Let's go on foot.
你听到了
You heard her.
你在想什么
What the hell were you thinking?
- 快走 - 你有病啊
- Walk! Come on. - What is your problem?
- 倒车不看路吗 - 搞定那家伙
- You don't look when you're backin' up? - Take care of that guy.
谁要赔我
Who's gonna pay for that?
别激动 老兄
Easy, fella. Easy.
继续走
Keep movin'.
没看到我的小黄吗
Can't you see my cab? It's yellow.
你得付板金的钱
No, you're gonna have to pay for this bodywork, man. I don't…
要和平…
Peace now! Peace now!
停战 停止对抗
Stop the war! Stop the fighting!
- 要去哪 梅森 - 走这边
- Where are we going, Mason? - This way.
- 我们不上战场 - 闭嘴
- Hell no, we won't go. - Shut up.
- 我们不上战场 - 绝不
- Hell no, we won't go! - Hell no!
- 我们不上战场 - 我们不上战场
- Hell no, we won't go! - Hell no, we won't go!
不上战场
We won't go!
- 我们不上战场 - 我们不上战场
- Hell no, we won't go! - Hell no, we won't go!
- 我们… - 闭嘴
- Hell no… - Shut up!
我们不上…
Hell no…
喂
Hey!
警察先生 救我
Officer! Help me!
警察先生 有枪击…
Officer, there was a shooting…
- 好 - 早上在亨特学院
- All right, all right. - …this morning at Hunter.
有人死了 该死
People are dead. God damn it.
- 有流氓闯进… - 先生 冷静点
- Some rogue maniacs broke in and… - Sir, you need to calm it down.
请听我说
Please listen to me.
早上发生枪击案
There was a shooting this morning, and the…
他们就在角落的联合爱迪生厢型车上
They're in a Con Ed van right around the corner!
你想干嘛
Hey! What do you think you're doing?
- 小心 - 他在干嘛
- Watch out! - What's he doin'?
你成功了
You did it!
让开
Move, out the way!
小心
Watch out!
快走开
Move! Quickly!
走开…
Move! Move!
快跑…
Go, go, go!
拜托 太扯了 是马
Come on. That's ridiculous. It's a horse.
停
Come on!
- 先生 - 让开
- Hey, mister. - Move! Out of the way!
拉住我的马
Hold my horse.
让开…
Move! Move!
可转乘皇后区大道线
Transfer is available for IND Queens Boulevard.
下一站 第59街莱辛顿大道站
Next stop, 59th, Lexington Avenue.
地铁比较快
Subway is faster.
人往往把科学浪漫化 其实它很冷酷
People tend to romanticize science, when it is, in fact, quite cold.
下一步呢 史密兹博士
So, what's next, Dr. Schmidt?
上火星
Mars?
不 我们征服了太空
No, we've conquered space.
现在要进军下一个领域
I'm moving to the next frontier.
太空之外还有什么
What's beyond space?
您可能得熨一下西装 史密兹博士
You might wanna get that suit pressed, Dr. Schmidt.
一小时后前往机场
We leave for the airport in an hour.
他要见总统
He's gonna meet the President.
如果总统在意几条皱折
If the President objects to a few creases…
或许该另请高明
perhaps he should find himself another physicist.
- 我能引用这句话吗 - 不行
- Can I use that? - No.
可以
Yes.
贝斯特
Baxter.
您的电话 博士
It's for you, Doctor.
我可能要晚点才去洛杉矶
I may wanna leave a bit later for Los Angeles.
我在等一件快递
I'm expecting a delivery shortly.
请说
Speak.
你的那些饭桶乱搞一通
Your goons made a mess.
是吗
Did they?
萧小姐见了一位琼斯教授
Miss Shaw met with a professor. Jones.
她从他手上拿到那个装置
She acquired the device from him.
我们追丢了
Then we lost her.
琼斯博士也跑了
Dr. Jones got away as well.
是吗
Is that so?
真可惜
Most unfortunate.
我得收拾残局 博士
I gotta clean things up here, Doctor.
身为美国政府代表
And as a representative of the United States government…
我建议你乖乖配合
I urge you to cooperate.
搭机到洛杉矶
Get on that plane to Los Angeles…
从总统手中领取奖章
and get your medal from the President.
喂
Hello?
打给我们的朋友 安排私人专机
Call our friends and secure a private charter.
到摩洛哥
To Morocco.
是
Yes, sir.
大学命案发生在游行高潮
The university murders took place at the height of the parade.
警方正在寻找退休教授亨利·琼斯博士
Police are searching for retired professor Dr. Henry Jones.
琼斯的同事告诉本台 他刚失去儿子
A colleague told ABC that Jones recently lost his son…
正在办离婚
and was in the middle of a divorce.
这个人长得好像你
This guy, he looks like you.
不像
Nah. No.
就是你
It is you.
不是…
No, no, no. Hey.
- 回家吧 你醉了 - 就是他
- Go home, pal. You're drunk. - This is the guy!
- 喂 - 凶手
- Hey! - It's the killer!
抱歉我迟到了 印第
Sorry I'm late, Indy.
桥上堵车
Bridge traffic.
真高兴见到你 萨拉
Boy, am I glad to see you, Sallah.
但愿我也能这么说 老朋友
I wish I could say the same, old friend.
印第 快进来
Quickly, Indy. Inside.
你的干女儿海伦娜
Your goddaughter, Helena…
去年在丹吉尔被捕
was arrested in Tangier last year…
罪名是拍卖走私品
for auctioning contraband.
还有
There's more.
保她出来的是阿济兹·拉辛
She was bailed out by Aziz Rahim.
阿济兹·拉辛的父亲是大拉辛
Aziz Rahim is the son of Big Rahim…
知名的摩洛哥黑帮分子
a well-known Moroccan mobster.
大拉辛拥有丹吉尔的…
Big Rahim owns the Hotel Atlantique…
大西洋饭店 这个星期
in Tangier, and this week…
该饭店要举行年度拍卖
the hotel is hosting its annual auction…
销售遭窃的古董
of stolen antiquities.
大咖都已经到了
All the big players are already there.
艾莉亚 贾巴利
Alia, Jabari.
这是战时带我们家到美国的大好人
This is the great man who brought our family to America during the war.
快答 苏伊士运河危机发生在何时
Quick, when was the Suez Crisis?
1956年
1956.
好厉害 贾巴利
Very impressive, Jabari.
我孙子看太多电视
My grandchildren watch too much TV…
但他们了解自己的历史
but they know their history.
他们懂怎么当埃及裔美国人
They understand what it is to be American and Egyptian.
我需要车子载我到机场 萨拉
I need a ride to the airport, Sallah.
如果你逃走 警方会认定你畏罪潜逃
If you run, the police will assume that you're guilty.
没有海伦娜和轮盘 我会被诬陷杀人
Without Helena or the Dial, I'm gonna get framed for murder.
你想过打给玛莉安吗
Have you thought about calling Marion?
她不想跟我说话
She doesn't wanna talk to me.
欢迎莅临纽约甘乃迪国际机场
Welcome to New York's John F. Kennedy International Airport.
上层仅供泛美航空乘客下车
The upper level is for Pan American Airlines passenger drop off only.
我从你的公寓拿了别的东西
I took something else from your apartment.
在床底下
It was under the bed.
谢了 萨拉
Thanks, Sallah.
我也带了护照
I also brought my passport.
我能帮你
I could help you.
在丹吉尔
In Tangier?
不管在哪里
Wherever chance takes us.
印第 我…
Indy, I…
我怀念沙漠
I miss the desert.
我怀念大海
I miss the sea.
我怀念每天早上醒来
And I miss waking up every morning…
想着新的一天会有什么美好冒险
wondering what wonderful adventure the new day will bring to us.
这不是冒险 萨拉
This is not an adventure, Sallah.
那种日子过去了
Those days have come and gone.
或许吧
Perhaps.
或许没有
Perhaps not.
给他们好看 印第安纳·琼斯
Give 'em hell, Indiana Jones!
香槟吗
Champagne?
四小时后抵达丹吉尔
We've got four more hours to Tangier.
您的苏格兰威士忌 先生
Your scotch, sir.
谢谢
Thanks.
贝索 快点
Basil. Come on, Baz!
- 开门 - 不要
- Open the door! - No!
- 别进来 印第 - 开门
- Stay out, Indy! - Open the door.
德国人说得对 印第
The Germans were right, Indy.
- 什么 - 它太大 太重要了
- What? - It's too big. It's too much.
喂…
Hey, Ba… Hey, hey!
- 老贝 给我 - 不
- Hey, Baz! Give me… - No.
- 你在干嘛 - 你没在听我说
- What are you doing? - You've listened to nothing that I said.
我不懂 老贝
I don't understand it, Baz!
我在楼下想解释给你听
Well, I was trying to explain it to you downstairs.
- 你充耳不闻 - 你吓坏你女儿了
- You've just ignored everything. - You're terrifying your daughter.
印第 阿基米德…
Indy, Archimedes…
发现了一种时间气象学
discovered a temporal meteorology.
阿基米德是数学家 老贝
Archimedes was a mathematician, Baz…
不是魔术师
not a magician.
他能预测时间的裂缝
He could predict fissures in time.
时间的裂缝
Fissures in time?
- 老贝 你无法证明 - 还没
- Baz, you can't prove that! - Well, not yet.
能证明才叫科学
Proving it is what makes it science!
老贝
Oh, Baz.
我根本不该给你这玩意
I never should've given you the thing.
它应该放在博物馆
It belongs in a museum.
拜托交给我
Give it to me. Please.
如果我给你
If I give you this…
你得摧毁它
it must be destroyed.
我会的
I will.
我会摧毁它 老贝
I'll destroy it, Baz.
你保证
Promise.
不好意思
I'm sorry about this.
都是我的错
It's all my fault.
- 你会在这里吗 - 会
- Are you gonna be here? - Yes, sir.
好 我得赶飞机
Okay. I've gotta catch an airplane.
若有人发现格拉飞科 他们会有两半
If anyone finds the Grafikos, they'll have both halves.
有些东西不该曝光
Some things should stay buried.
我知道 老贝
I know, Baz.
- 非摧毁它不可 - 我会的
- It's vital that you destroy it. - I will, Baz.
- 你懂吗 - 我会摧毁它
- Do you understand? - I'll destroy it.
- 说你会 印第 - 对
- Say you will, Indy. - Yes.
我会 对
I will… Yes.
你答应我的 别忘了
You promised me. Remember that.
我保证
I will… I promise.
有原因…
There's a reason…
阿基米德将它一分为二是有原因的
a reason that Archimedes broke it in two.
我知道 老贝
I know, Baz.
印第
Indy.
谢了 袋熊
Thanks, Wombat.
他过几天就没事了
He's gonna be all right in a few days.
我一降落就打给你
I'll call you as soon as I land.
各位先生女士
Ladies and gentlemen…
我们将于20分钟后在丹吉尔降落
we are 20 minutes from landing in Tangier.
- 别喝了 - 你干嘛
- Stop drinking! - What are you doing?
别再喝香槟了 你还要…
No more champagne! How many more…
我要留下
I'm staying.
回家 回去
Go home. Go home!
萧小姐 她在这里
Miss Shaw, she's here.
以青铜制成
Forged in bronze.
近乎完整
Nearly complete.
它是一个天文钟
It is an astrological clock.
来自公元前三世纪
Dating third century BC…
由阿基米德亲手打造
and built by Archimedes himself.
起标价2万
All right, let's start at 20, 000.
2万 谢谢您
20, 000, thank you very much.
3万 3万
30.30.
数据正常
Gauges green…
马力满档
power full…
时速达到85英里就仰转
and when I reach 85, I rotate.
再来呢
What next?
- 路易 帮他 好可爱 - 拉回驾驶盘
- Louis, help him! He's so cute. - Pull back on the yoke.
- 有 我起飞了 - 他起飞了
- I did, man. I'm airborne. - Yeah, he's airborne.
- 我喝一口 - 要收回襟翼吗
- Can I have a sip? - Do I pick up the flaps?
在400尺以下别碰襟翼
Don't touch the flaps under 400 feet.
缩小俯仰角 时速升到120英里
Decrease your pitch to get to 120.
好
All right.
- 私人拍卖会 老先生 - 我得进去
- Private auction, old timer. - I've gotta get in there.
说出通关密语才能进去 这是规定
No password, no entry. I don't make the rules.
- 目前出价多少 - 5万
- And what is the current bid? - The bid is 50, 000.
那我出5万5
Then I bid 55.
- 谁出6万 - 6万
- Who'll give me 60? - 60.
6万 6万5呢
60.65?
- 6万5、7万 - 7万5
- 65.70? - 75.
- 7万5 8万 - 8万
- 75.80? - 80.
- 8万5 - 9万呢
- 85. - How about 90?
这是私人拍卖会
This auction is private.
拍卖结束了
This auction's over.
正好相反 刚开始
Au contraire, it's hardly begun.
- 10万 - 10万
- 100. - 100, 000.
我喜欢这顶帽子
I like the hat, by the way.
让你年轻至少两岁
Makes you look at least two years younger.
谢谢
Thanks.
- 11万 赞 - 我说拍卖结束了
- 110, bravo. - I told you that this auction is over.
请问这个人是谁
Excuse me, who is this man?
- 我是她干爹 - 他算亲戚
- I'm her godfather. - He's mildly related.
超过她的睡觉时间了
And she's up past her bedtime.
- 走吧 袋熊 - 劝你别这样
- Come on, Wombat. - I wouldn't do that.
想到酒吧解释给警察听吗
You want to explain it to the cops at the bar?
我花钱打点过的那些
The ones I paid off?
你搞不清楚状况 琼斯哥
You're out of your depth, Jonesy.
- 琼斯哥 - 他以为我犯法
- "Jonesy"? - He thinks I'm a criminal.
他才是命案通缉犯
He's the one wanted for murder.
报上的大头照挺帅的 13万
Nice big picture in the New York Herald. 130?
我没杀人
I didn't kill anyone.
- 私人拍卖不得进入 - 你心里有数
- No entry, it's a private auction. - And you know it, Helena.
凶手正在找这个
But whoever did was looking for this.
你拿的是潘朵拉的盒子
What you've got here is Pandora's Box.
并不是
No, actually.
它是我的盒子
It's my box.
你
You.
我们见过吗
Have we met?
没有
No.
我记忆有点模糊
My memory is a little fuzzy…
但你很面熟
but your face rings a bell.
你还是纳粹吗
Are you still a Nazi?
你搞混了 在下史密兹
You're confused. My name is Schmidt.
阿拉巴马大学的史密兹教授
Professor Schmidt of Alabama University.
史密兹教授
Professor Schmidt.
很高兴见到你本人
How nice to meet you in person.
- 15万 - 我们谈过之后
- 150. - After our conversation, Miss Shaw…
我以为我们对轮盘达成协议
I thought we'd come to an agreement about the Dial.
奇了 上次有个很像你的人
Funny. The last time I saw the other guy who looks like you…
他也在找这东西
he was also after this.
你原本出价不高 史密兹教授
Your numbers were light, Professor Schmidt.
幸好你来了
But good news is, you're here now.
- 出价16万 - 你好像不懂 萧小姐
- The bid is 160. - You don't seem to understand, Miss Shaw.
这件文物是我的资产
This relic is my property.
才怪 你用偷的
It's not yours. You stole it.
然后你又偷走
Then you stole it.
然后我又偷走 这就是资本主义
And then I stole it. It's called capitalism.
出价16万
The bid is 160.
- 16万 - 17万
- 160. - 170?
你该待在纽约才对
You should've stayed in New York.
- 17万 - 你们不该染指波兰
- 170? - You should've stayed out of Poland.
17万 有人要加价吗
170. Anyone? Anyone?
一次 两次…
Going, going…
成交
Gone!
走开
Stay away!
快拿轮盘
Get the Dial.
走开
Stay away!
你好 克劳
Oh, hello, Claude.
你不该回来的 海伦娜
You should not have come back, Helena.
别插手
Get back.
泰迪
Teddy!
拉辛叫你留下
Rahim says you stay.
谢谢
Thank you.
到过去相见了 琼斯博士
See you in the past, Dr. Jones.
快 让开
Move! Get out of the way!
我的出租车
It's my cab!
叫他们走开
Tell them to back off.
我刚叫他们朝你开枪
I just told them to shoot you.
好 各位
All right, guys.
把枪放下
Put the guns down.
放下
Put 'em down.
好
All right.
这样好多了
That's better.
天啊
Oh, dear.
拉辛
Rahim.
你穿睡衣
You're in pajamas.
我在睡觉 海伦娜
I was sleeping, Helena.
睡得很甜
Peacefully.
然后我爸叫醒我
Then my father woke me.
他说你回饭店了
He told me you'd returned to our hotel.
接着他给我这把弯刀
Then he handed me this scimitar…
叫我提你的人头回家
and told me to come home with your head.
一定要是头吗
Does it have to be that bit?
我以为你是爱我才回来
I thought maybe you returned because you loved me.
拉辛
Rahim…
我有个物件要卖
I had an item to sell.
抱歉 她说的物件
Excuse me. The item she's talking about…
- 其实是我的 - 你不必…
- actually belongs to me. - No. You do not need to…
- 有些大坏蛋 - 硬要插话
- And some very bad people… - …intrude in this conversation.
- 更恶劣的人抢走了 - 少管闲事 我的生意
- …worse people, have run off with it. - You do not need to get involved with my business.
这是你的新欢吗
Is this your new man?
- 不是 - 说来复杂
- No. No, no. - It's complicated.
你到底欠他什么
What exactly do you owe this guy?
一些保释金和一生的幸福
Just some bail money and a lifetime of happiness.
我敢说你把戒指卖了
I presume you sold the ring.
价钱没我想的高
It didn't go for as much as I thought it would.
我会动手
I'll do it!
你想…喂
What are you… Hey!
你差点害死我
You just got me killed!
我可没跟黑道订婚
Well, I'm not the one that's engaged to a mobster!
盗墓老贼凭什么说三道四
I don't need morality lessons from an aging grave robber!
我不是盗墓老贼
I'm not a grave robber.
你爸和我一起做过重要的工作
Your father and I did important work together.
别说你那些冒险都是高贵无私的壮举
Don't tell me all your escapades were noble, selfless quests.
你是为了追求刺激
You did it for the buzz!
干得好 泰迪
Oh, good work, Teddy!
- 过去 小鬼 - 喂
- Move over, kid. - Hey!
- 海伦娜 - 倒车…
- Helena! - Back up! Back up!
不是往这边
Not this way!
你根本乱开 印第
You don't know where you're going, Indy!
- 听他的 他地头蛇 - 丹吉尔我很熟
- Listen to him. He knows this town! - I know Tangier!
他在那里
There he is!
快 再快点
Faster. Go faster!
十分钟到机场 老大
Ten minutes to the airport, boss.
我不确定史密兹是不是教授
I'm not sure Professor Schmidt is an actual professor, by the way.
- 他是纳粹 - 左转
- He's a Nazi! - Turn left!
左转…
Turn left! Turn left!
- 不对 - 不
- Oh, no! - No!
海伦娜 别闹了
Helena! Don't do this!
- 这边 - 那边
- Hey, this way! - That way!
不
No!
海伦娜
Helena!
不
No!
搞什么
What the hell?
海伦娜
Helena!
喂
Hey!
搞什么
What the hell?
快啊
Come on!
快走…
Come on. Come on!
你想他会感到骄傲吗
You think he'd be proud of this?
谁
Who?
你老爸
Your father!
他的独生女为了保释金出卖灵魂
His only daughter selling her soul for bail money!
这样说还挺不赖的
Sounds quite cool when you put it like that.
那不全是保释金
And it's not all bail money.
- 有的是赌债 - 谢谢哦 泰迪
- Some of it's gambling debt and some… - Thank you, Teddy.
海伦娜 不要
Helena! No!
海伦娜
Helena!
你怎么沦落到这地步
How did you end up like this?
你是说足智多谋吗
Well, you mean resourceful?
大胆 美丽 独立自主
Daring? Beautiful? Self-sufficient?
抓紧
Hold on!
走这边
Go this way!
他在那里
There he is.
- 停车 - 喂
- Stop! Stop! - Hey! Hey!
在左边
On the left!
泰迪 你来开
Take the wheel, Teddy!
你要干嘛
What are you doing?
把我的东西抢回来
Getting what's mine.
海伦娜
Helena!
可恶 你疯啦
Damn it! You crazy?
海伦娜
Hey! Helena!
- 拿枪 - 萧小姐
- Take the gun! - Miss Shaw.
放手 萧小姐
Let go, Miss Shaw!
放手
Let go.
快点 轮盘给我
Come on! Give me the Dial!
海伦娜
Helena!
该死
Damn.
- 调头 他们往那边 - 他走了
- Turn back! They went that way! - He's gone!
- 让开 - 喂
- Move over! - Hey!
我不是来从你未婚夫手中拯救你
I didn't come here to rescue you from your fiancé!
拯救我
Rescue me?
我只想拿回轮盘
I just want the Dial back.
手举高
Put your hands above your head.
我们分手得不太漂亮
Not the smoothest break-up I ever had.
- 如果你爸还活着 - 可惜没有 印第
- If your father was still alive… - Well, he's not, Indy.
引擎有问题
Hey, something's wrong with the engine.
但愿有个像我父亲的人
If only there'd been someone there for me, some father figure…
特别选定担任这角色的人
someone specifically anointed for the job.
- 你不知道… - 不用自责
- You have no idea about the kind… - Don't beat yourself up about it.
干爹到底是什么
I mean, what even is a godfather?
你本来就不懂跟家人相处
Anyway, family never was your strong suit.
- 几点了 - 嗯…
- What is the time, by the way? - It's…
不公平
Hey, no fair.
还给我
Give me that back.
那是我爸的表
That was my father's watch!
还给他
Give it back to him.
你得自己离开
You're gonna have to leave town with me.
拉辛也会找你
Rahim will be looking for you too.
他们会先去丹吉尔机场
They'll go to Tangier airport first…
我们得搭火车 到卡萨布兰加搭机
so we'll need to catch a train and get a plane from Casablanca.
什么声音
What was that?
可恶
Damn.
是
Yeah.
我知道
I know, sir.
他的…
Yes…
了解
Copy.
他们下令停止
They pulled the plug.
你吓到他们了
You got them scared.
- 因为他们不懂 - 不对
- Because they don't understand. - No.
因为你的同事杀了三个美国平民
Because your associates killed three American civilians…
轰炸全国转播的游行
and blew up a nationally televised parade.
因为你放美国总统鸽子
Because you stood up the President of the United States…
跑到摩洛哥
ran to Morocco…
引发一场需要军事撤离的事件
and created an incident that required military extraction!
那就带我到华府去解释
Then take me to DC, and I will explain it all.
他们要你消失
They want you to vanish.
现在一半的轮盘到手了
We have half the Dial now.
他们只是想让你开心
They were just trying to keep you happy…
让你去追那样东西
letting you chase that thing.
他们根本不在乎它
They never cared about it.
会的 等他们明白它的威力
They will, Miss Mason, when they understand what it can do.
你让人类上月球
You put them on the moon.
他们达到目的了
They got what they wanted.
系好安全带 准备降落西班牙
All right, buckle up. We're landing in Spain.
C9运输机会送你去麦斯威尔
C-9 transport will take you from there to Maxwell.
我不回阿拉巴马
I'm not going back to Alabama!
我们只需要一艘船去地中海
All we need is a vessel to take us to the Mediterranean.
格拉飞科会带我们去其他…
The Grafikos will take us to the other…
拜托 梅森小姐 拜托
Please, Miss Mason. Please.
放开我 史密兹
Let go of me, Schmidt.
我个人请求你
I'm asking you personally.
你真难搞 博士
You're a piece of work, Doc.
喂
Hey!
史密兹
Schmidt…
我姓佛勒
My name is Voller.
尤根`佛勒
Jürgen Voller.
那是海种马
That's a Sea Stallion.
美军直升机
American helicopter.
你知道莱特兄弟吗
Did you know the Wright Brothers?
- 什么 - 莱特兄弟
- What? - The Wright Brothers.
奥维尔和威布尔
Orville and Wilbur.
他们发明飞机 住在印第安纳州
They invented the airplane, and they lived in Indiana.
威布尔在印第安纳出生
Wilbur was born in Indiana.
我不是印第安纳人 泰迪
I'm not from Indiana, Teddy.
莱特兄弟出生于南北战争时期
And the Wright Brothers were born during the Civil War.
我以为你可能是他们同学
Oh, I thought maybe you went to school with them.
拜托 印第 挺好笑的
Oh, come on, Indy. That was funny.
好笑
"Funny"?
我跟抛锚嘟嘟车和两个贼困在丹吉尔
I'm stuck in Tangier with a broken tuk-tuk and two thieves.
因为命案遭通缉
I'm wanted for murder.
纳粹拿到半个阿基米德轮盘
Nazis have half of Archimedes' Dial…
还有你爸的笔记本
and your father's notebooks.
我有副本
I have a copy.
爸的笔记本 我抄了一份
Dad's notebooks. I made a copy.
在哪
Where?
你背下五本笔记
You memorized five notebooks?
七本 当然没有
Seven. And of course not.
其中一半无聊到爆
Half of them were as dull as ditch water.
我只背重要的部分
Just the really important bits.
譬如
Like what?
格拉飞科的位置
The location of the Grafikos.
没人知道格拉飞科在哪里
Nobody knows where the Grafikos is.
- 爸知道 - 才怪
- Dad did. - No, he didn't.
- 他知道 - 不知道
- Yes, he did. - No, he didn't.
- 他知道 - 格拉飞科是什么
- Yes, he did. - What's a Grafikos?
找到其余轮盘的指南
It's directions to the rest of the Dial.
问她用哪种语言写的
Ask her if she knows what language it's in.
不是语言 是密码
It isn't in a language. It's in a code.
什么密码
What code?
阿基米德使用两种密码
Archimedes used two codes.
线形文字B和波利比奥斯方阵密码
Linear B and Polybius Square.
就算你找到 没有我你也看不懂
So, even if you find the Grafikos, without me, you can't read it.
拜托
Please.
爸在我九岁时教我波利比奥斯
Dad taught me Polybius when I was nine.
他在家里到处留下小字条
Used to leave little notes around the house.
「整理房间」
"Tidy your room."
「别碰我的白兰地」
"Stay away from my brandy."
如果那是线形文字B呢
What if it's Linear B?
我打赌是波利比奥斯
50 quid it's Polybius.
给我
Give me that.
喂
Hey.
没用啦
That won't work.
摩洛哥人嚼铁线子树汁做的口香糖
Moroccan chewing gum's made from the sap of the Manilkara.
它能抗热
Heat resistant.
发动看看
Try and start it.
- 发动 - 我在试了
- Start it. - I am.
怎样
Huh? Huh?
- 怎样 - 撑不久的
- Huh? - It won't hold.
能载我们到火车站
It'll get us to the train station.
我们
"Us"?
- 你要回家 - 不是
- You goin' home? - No.
我要去卡萨布兰加
I'm going to Casablanca.
然后搭飞机去爱琴海
Then I'm gonna hop a plane to the Aegean.
跟你一样
Just like you.
我们干嘛去爱琴海
What makes you think we're going to the Aegean?
你得抢在纳粹之前找到格拉飞科
You gotta get to the Grafikos before the Nazis.
阿基米德被罗马人包围
Archimedes was surrounded by Romans.
它还会在哪里
Where else would it be?
爱琴海很大 印第
The Aegean is huge, Indy.
你也没座标
And you don't have coordinates.
你没有船
And you don't have a boat.
我在希腊有个老朋友
I've got an old friend in Greece.
专业潜水夫
An expert diver.
有一艘又大又漂亮的船
With a big, beautiful boat…
能抢在他们之前载我们过去
that'll get us there before they will.
你需要我
You need me…
你很清楚
and you know it.
（丹吉尔）
（卡萨布兰加）
（意大利）
（希腊）
（雅典）
瑞尼
Renny!
印第
Indy?
Indy!
那就是专业潜水夫
So, that's the expert diver?
西班牙头号蛙人
Spain's greatest frogman.
嘿
Hey!
西班牙头号蛙人只有破船和一条腿
So, Spain's greatest frogman has a shit boat and only one good frog leg?
别乱讲
Stop it.
你换船了
You got a different boat.
少罗唆
Stop it.
我们要去这里
We're going here.
他们发现部分安提基瑟拉仪的地方
Where they found the first part of the Antikythera.
可是…
But…
我们要潜得更深
we're going deeper.
我爸找到发现轮盘的海绵潜水夫
Dad tracked down the old sponge diver who found the Dial.
他跟他说…
He told him…
那艘罗马沉船解体的地点在…
that the wrecked Roman ship broke up under the sea…
海面下20米
70 feet below.
里面有100多个罗马百夫长的骨骸
Filled with the skeletons of over 100 centurions.
这是他们发现它的地方
That's where they found it.
但他说船只大部分都瓦解了
But he said that most of the ship had broken off…
沉入海床
and sunk to the ocean floor.
海绵潜水夫下不去
Too deep for sponge divers.
爸开始想一艘罗马战舰
So, Dad started wondering why a Roman warship…
为何会载100个百夫长离开叙拉古
would sail out of Syracuse with 100 centurions on board.
他们不是带半个轮盘去兜风的
They weren't taking half a Dial for a joyride.
他们有格拉飞科
They had the Grafikos…
想找另一半的轮盘
and they were looking for the rest of the Dial.
你爸真是天才
Your dad was a genius.
对
Yeah.
他是
He was.
黑桃7
Seven of spades.
你怎么知道
How do you do that?
哇
Wow.
再来一次
Do it again.
选一张 琼斯博士
Pick a card, Dr. Jones.
黑桃7
Seven of spades!
她太神了
She's magic.
魔术牌
Trick deck.
不是
No.
我操控选牌过程
I force the card.
我给冤大头…
I offer the mark…
也就是你
you…
有选择的感觉
the feeling of a choice…
但最后我让你挑中我要的牌
but ultimately, I make you pick the card I want.
冤大头
"The mark."
对 明天是大日子
Yeah. Tomorrow is a big day.
我得检查氧气管
I have to check the lines.
晚安
Good night.
你记得你爸的笔记里有什么日期吗
You remember seeing any dates in your father's notebooks?
日期
Dates?
什么日期
What dates?
这些日期
These dates.
这封信上一再写到
Written over and over again in this letter.
1969年8月20日
August 20th, 1969.
距离现在三天
That's three days from now.
还有1939年同一天
And the same date in 1939.
希特勒入侵波兰前两周
Two weeks before Hitler invades Poland.
等等
Wait.
现在你相信轮盘有魔力了
Now you believe the Dial has magical powers?
我不相信魔法 袋熊
I don't believe in magic, Wombat.
但这辈子见识过几次
But a few times in my life, I've seen things.
我无法解释的事情
Things I can't explain.
我渐渐认为重点不在…
And I've come to believe it's not so much…
你相信什么
what you believe.
而是你有多么相信
It's how hard you believe it.
我也见识过一些事 印第
I've seen things too, Indy.
世上唯一值得相信的
The only thing worth believing in, ever…
就是钱
is cash.
对
Right.
要是能回到过去呢
What if you could go back in time?
你会做什么
What would you do?
见证特洛伊战争
Witness the Trojan War?
跟埃及艳后见面
Check in on Cleopatra?
我会阻止我儿子入伍
I'd stop my son from enlisting.
他从军是为了讨好你吗
Did he sign up to please you?
不 为了惹火我
No, he signed up to piss me off.
你会怎么阻止他
How would you have stopped him?
跟他说他会没命
I'd tell him he was gonna die.
跟他说他的母亲会…
I'd tell him that his mother would…
伤心一辈子
find no end to her grief.
他的父亲会…
And that his father would be…
无法安慰她
helpless to console her.
他们的婚姻也会因此告终
And that the loss would put an end to their marriage.
你还戴着婚戒
You're still wearing the ring.
有搞头
Promising.
更有搞头
More promising.
你好啊
Hello.
穿好装备 他们在等
Get your gear on. They're waiting.
嗨
Hey.
过来
Come here.
好
Okay.
给你看个东西
I'm gonna show you something.
这看起来好重要
Gosh, this looks important.
绳子绕过来
Around the rope…
我们会潜得很深
Now, we are going deep.
快速下降 透过这些管子呼吸
Descend fast, and breathe through these hoses.
懂吗
Okay?
彼此要分开
Stay separate.
不要互相交错 好吗
No crisscross. All right?
不能待太久
We cannot stay long.
我有个方法 通常能避免潜水夫病
I have a method that usually prevents the bends.
- 通常 - 对
- Usually? - Yeah.
我称为「弹跳」
I call it "the bounce."
快速下降
You know, fast down…
三分钟到底部 然后上来
three minutes on the bottom, and then up.
三分钟
Three minutes!
一秒都不多
No one more second.
三分钟
Three minutes.
没错
Yeah, that's right.
- 我的打火机呢 - 不知道 船长
- Where is my lighter? - I don't know, capitán.
该出发了
We have to go.
先问一下
Quick question.
那是什么
What's that?
- 鲨鱼吗 - 不是
- They're sharks? - No.
这里没有鲨鱼 是鳗鱼
No, no. No sharks here. Eels.
鳗鱼
Eels?
欧洲鳗
Anguilas.
大部分都很小
Most are small.
大的会有两米
Sometimes they are big. Two meters.
看到它们就别动
But if you see them, stay still.
它们咬人会紧咬不放
They bite you, they lock the jaw. Yeah.
看起来很像蛇
They look like snakes.
才怪
No, they don't.
上兵白兰地报到
Private Brandy reporting for duty.
你不去吗 泰迪
You're not coming, Teddy?
我不会游泳
I can't swim.
算他好运
Lucky him.
谁都能游泳
Everyone can swim.
手臂伸出收回 伸出收回
Reach and pull. Reach and pull.
你跟海特注意我们的管子
All right. You stay here with Hector and watch our lines.
时间到了 各位
It is time, camarada.
两分钟
Two minutes?
拿到了
I got it.
喂
Hey.
快点
Hurry up!
海伦娜
Helena!
上来
Come on.
对…
That's it. That's it. That's it.
对
That's it.
这些人是谁
Who are these people?
纳粹
Nazis.
琼斯博士 你先还给我轮盘
First, you return my Dial, Dr. Jones…
现在又带格拉飞科给我
and now, you bring me the Grafikos.
很高兴你退休后还是一尾活龙
I'm very happy you're not wasting in retirement.
我有机会就该杀了你
I should have retired you when I had the chance.
你的赞助者呢
Where are your sponsors?
我现在独立作业
I'm on my own now.
时间往前走 琼斯博士
Things move forward, Dr. Jones.
有时候
And sometimes…
往后退
they go backward.
我们坐下来好好聊聊
Now, let's get comfortable and have a little talk.
那是什么语言
What language is that?
这不是语言
It's not a language.
是密码
It's a code.
波利比奥斯
Polybius.
你欠我50镑
You owe me 50 quid.
波利比奥斯密码不熟吗
Not familiar with Polybius cipher?
不熟
No.
看起来你熟
But it appears you are.
请看一下
Read it, please.
不要
No.
印第
Indy…
现在想帮忙了吗
Feeling helpful now?
我想
I am.
我倒背如流
I know this stuff backwards.
不要
No!
抱歉 印第
Sorry, Indy.
我不会壮烈牺牲
I don't do noble death.
只做…
Just…
冷酷无情的数学
cold, hard maths.
我破解密码 帮你找到另一半
I crack the code, help you find the other half.
10万 付现
One hundred grand. Cash.
海伦娜
Helena…
不要拉倒
Take it or leave it.
一言为定
You have a deal.
他绝对不会付钱给你
He'll never pay you.
你会发现这比你要的价钱更有价值
I think you will find this is worth more than your asking price.
- 泰迪 - 海伦娜
- Teddy. - Helena…
不要这么做
don't do this.
来解密吧
Let's see what we've got here.
「我的马卡纳…」
"My Makhana…"
意思是「机器」
That's "machine"…
「留在我身旁 在我离开的城市
"lies with me, in the city I left.
那里的狼教人走路
"Where wolves teach men to walk."
我躺在九之一底下」
"Under one of nine, I lie."
只有一种东西能永远躺着
Only one thing lies anywhere forever.
死人 如果轮盘留在他身旁
The dead. So, if the Dial lies with him, then…
这是前往他陵墓的指引
then this is directions to his tomb.
阿基米德之墓
The Tomb of Archimedes?
两千年来无人发现
Undiscovered for two millennia.
「我离开的城市」
"The city I left."
阿基米德生前住过两个地方
Archimedes lived two places his entire life,
所以他只离开一个
so he only left one.
有人知道吗 后面的
Anyone? At the back?
拜托 印第 大家都知道
Come on, Indy. Everyone knows this.
包括这个小丑
Even this clown.
亚历山大
Alexandria.
100分
Full marks.
狼的希腊文是「莱可斯」
Now, "wolf" in Greek is "lycos."
就是「学校」的字根
Root of the word "lycaeum" or "school."
「走路」的多利克文是…
And the Doric for "walking" is…
「佩利提欧」
"peripatio."
这个字刚好也是…
Which also happens to be the word for…
我以为你博学多闻呢
I thought you were a bright spark.
「佩利提欧」意思是「走路」
"Peripatio" means "walking"…
但也有「计算」的意思
but it also means "counting."
所以「狼教人走路」
So, "Where wolves teach men to walk"…
- 可能是… - 数学学院
- could be… - The School of Mathematics.
没错
Is correct.
下一句就简单了
Now, the next bit is easy.
「躺在九之一底下」
"Beneath one of nine"?
缪思有九个
There are nine Muses.
「缪思恩」
The Museon.
亚历山大大图书馆的希腊文
The Greek word for the Great Library of Alexandria.
我们知道有九尊雕像支撑着屋顶
Which, as we all know, has nine statues supporting its roof.
借我哈一口
May I?
谢谢
Thank you.
九个缪思女神 顺序倒过来
The nine Muses, in reverse order…
卡利俄佩
are Calliope…
乌拉妮亚
Urania…
波丽姆妮亚
Polymnia…
- 爱拉托 - 波丽姆妮亚
- Erato… - Polymnia.
梅莉什么的…
…and Meli whasisname…
另一个
that other one…
塔利亚
Thalia…
欧忒耳佩
Euteroe…
但第一个是…
but the first is…
克丽欧
Clio.
历史与时间的缪思
The Muse of history and time.
那个阿基米德…
That Archimedes…
好聪明的家伙
what a clever bugger.
陵墓入口在数学学院旁
The entrance to the tomb is by the School of Mathematics…
克丽欧雕像底下
under a statue of Clio…
亚历山大大图书馆遗址
in the ruins of the Great Library of Alexandria.
天才博士好棒棒
Gold star for Dr. Brains.
泰迪
Teddy!
格拉飞科 快去拿
The Grafikos, get it!
我以前说过 我要再说一次
I have said it before, and I will say it again!
走投无路 就用炸药
When you're in a tight spot, dynamite.
我朋友刚刚遇害
My friend was just murdered.
抱歉
Sorry.
你跟他们全招了
You told them everything.
一字不漏
Word for word.
但阿基米德没那么简单
But Archimedes didn't make it that easy.
陵墓不在亚历山大
The tomb isn't in Alexandria.
你看到什么
So, what do you see?
波利比奥斯方阵密码
Polybius square.
什么材料
Made of?
蜡和木头
Wax and wood.
还有呢
Anything else?
很重
It's heavy.
太重了
Too heavy.
给我
Give me that.
这是纯金
This is solid gold?
古老黄金
Ancient gold.
来自尼罗河
From the Nile.
拿一下 泰迪
Hold it, Teddy.
卖掉这玩意
Sell this thing…
还清债务还有剩
and we are out of the hole and then some.
我有客户会买
I have just the customer.
- 直布罗陀女公爵 - 送到博物馆
- Cranky, old Duchess in Gibraltar… - This is going in a museum.
你掌舵 泰迪
Take the wheel, Teddy.
上面写什么
What does it say?
「寻觅狄奥尼修斯…
"Search where Dionysius…
听见每个低语…
"hears each whisper…"
宛如飓风之处」
"like a hurricane."
耳朵
The Ear.
狄奥尼修斯洞穴
The cave of Dionysius.
在哪里
Where is that?
西西里
In Sicily.
- 我们有多少燃料 - 一整箱
- How much fuel have we got? - It's full.
他们往西走
They're heading west.
不是往东
Not east.
（西西里 叙拉古）
我要吃木瓜
I want the papaya.
多少钱
How much is it?
拿去
Take this.
看那个戴草帽的男孩
Look at that kid with the straw hat.
这边
This way.
嗨
Hey.
好看吗
What do you think?
我们在干嘛
What are we doing?
等洞穴关门
Waiting for closing time at the caves.
里面都是游客
It's crawling with tourists.
所以现在他是老大
Okay, so he's, like, running the show now?
他不是老大 泰迪
He's not running the show, Teddy.
我觉得我们做这件事的动机根本不对
I just thought we were in this for all the wrong reasons.
是不对
We are.
无庸置疑
Most assuredly.
他绝对不会让我们卖那玩意
You know he's never gonna let us sell any of that stuff.
状况还在我掌控中 泰迪
I'm still in charge, Teddy.
海伦娜 过来帮我一下
Helena, get over here! Give me a hand!
卯起来血拼哦
You splurged.
这是你的背包
Here's your backpack.
那个小鬼呢
Where's the kid?
小心点
Hey, watch it!
有毛病啊
What's wrong with you?
你好
Hello.
嗨
Hey.
放开我
Let me go!
放开我 让我走
Get off me! Let me go!
喂…
Hey, hey, hey!
海伦娜
Helena!
他们抓走泰迪了
They've got Teddy.
他们带他到山上
They took him up the hill somewhere.
他们会对他怎样
What are they gonna do to him?
他知道耳朵 格拉飞科写什么
He knows about the Ear, what the Grafikos says.
他们不会伤害他
They're not gonna hurt him.
他们会利用他
They're gonna use him…
拿到另一半轮盘
to get the other half of the Dial.
我们得抢先一步
We gotta get there first.
殖民女王在西西里建造许多城市
Colonizing queens built many cities in Sicily.
- 这座神殿… - 我们走
- The temple… - Let's go.
是最古老的希腊神殿
…is the oldest of the Greek temples.
洞穴在那边
The cave's over there.
能开快一点吗
Could we go a little faster, please?
狄奥尼修斯之耳
The Ear of Dionysius.
哇
Wow.
「寻觅狄奥尼修斯
"Search where Dionysius.
听见每个低语 宛如飓风之处」
hears each whisper like a hurricane."
好大的回音
That's some echo.
继续发出声音 看哪里最大声
Keep making noise till we find out where it's loudest.
停
Stop.
就是这里
This is it.
希腊三角楣饰
Greek pediment.
入口
An entrance.
以前是
Used to be.
新月
A crescent.
跟格拉飞科上的一样
Just like on the Grafikos.
我想上面有个开口
I think there's an opening up there.
你在上面还好吗
You okay up there?
还好
Yes.
你没动
You're not moving.
我在思考
I'm thinking.
思考什么
About?
我干嘛离地十几米
About what the hell I'm doing up here, 40 feet in the air…
肩膀明明快废了
with crap shoulders…
脊椎弯曲无力
crumbling vertebrae…
一腿装了骨板 一腿装螺丝
a plate in one leg, screws in the other.
我了解
Yeah, I get it. I get it.
你才不了解
No, you don't get it.
你年纪只有我的一半
You're half my age.
没被迫喝下迦梨的血
You haven't been forced to drink the blood of Kali.
对 有道理
No. Fair enough.
或惨遭巫毒教凌虐
Or been tortured with voodoo.
我猜你也没中弹九次
And I'm just guessing, but I don't think you've been shot nine times…
包括你父亲那一次
including once by your father.
我爸对你开枪了
Dad shot you?
别跟我说话
Don't talk to me.
快上去 我会跟上
Just go ahead. I'll follow you.
不…
No, no, no.
我们关闭了…
We are close. We are close.
看一下
Look around you.
- 关闭了 - 狄奥尼修斯洞穴
- We are close. - The Cave of Dionysius.
不…
No, no, no.
洞穴关闭整修
The cave is closed for renovation.
我再问一次
Let me ask again.
狄奥尼修斯洞穴在哪里
Where is the Cave of Dionysius?
怎样 担心那个小鬼吗
What's the matter? You worried about the kid?
你确定他们不会伤害他
Are you sure they won't hurt him?
他不会有事的
He'll be fine.
他很精明
He's smart.
你在哪找到他的
Where'd you find him?
他十岁在马拉喀什赌场外想偷我钱包
He tried to steal my purse outside a casino in Marrakesh when he was 10.
我不断用车门撞他
I hit him repeatedly with my car door…
他不放手 我也不罢休
but he didn't let go and neither did I.
后来就混在一起了
So, been together ever since.
我以为你只关心钱
Thought you were all about the money.
我是啊
I am.
没人会把亡父的笔记本背得滚瓜烂熟
Nobody memorizes every page of their dead father's notebooks…
只为了钱
for the money.
佛勒先生
Herr Voller!
他们往那边走
They went that way.
为什么
Why?
快啊…
Come on, come on.
我们走
Let's go.
天啊
Oh, my…
我的天啊
Oh, my God!
- 天啊 - 不…
- Oh, God! - No, no.
我的天啊…
Oh, my God! Oh, my God!
还在我身上吗
Are they off me?
- 把它们弄掉 - 不…
- Get 'em off! - No, no.
- 弄掉 - 等等
- Get 'em off! - Wait.
那是什么
What is that?
甲烷
Methane.
憋气
Don't breathe.
Don't breathe?
我们得赶快离开
We've gotta get outta here.
雅典娜
Athena.
战争女神
Goddess of war.
也是理性女神
And reason.
「在月亮底下
"Under the moon…"
生命在她脚边」
"life lies at her feet."
排水体积测量法
Water displacement.
进池里
Get in the pool!
为什么 帮我开门
Why? Help me open the door.
他们没从门出去
Well, they didn't get out the doors!
进来池子里
Get in the pool!
好 我进来
Okay, I'm getting in the pool.
帮帮我
Help me.
阿基米德非常着迷…
Archimedes was fascinated…
排水体积测量法
by water displacement!
回来
Hey! Get back here!
克雷柏
Klaber!
没必要这样
You don't need to do that.
喂
Hey!
给我
Give me that!
不
No!
别管他们
Leave them.
我说别管他们
I said leave them.
伸出拉回
Reach and pull.
阿基米德之墓
Archimedes' tomb.
抓住那一角
Grab that corner.
印第
Indy.
这檐壁饰带…
This frieze…
是凤凰
It's a phoenix.
常见的图像
A common icon.
不 不常见
No. Look, it isn't.
这只凤凰有螺旋桨
This phoenix has propellers.
它怎么会在这里
What's this doing here?
时钟在一千年后才发明出来
Clocks won't be invented for 1, 000 years…
更别说是表
much less watches.
阿基米德用过
Archimedes used it.
爸说得对
Dad was right.
它有用
It works.
当然有用 萧小姐
Of course it works, Miss Shaw.
数学是有用的
Mathematics works.
它战胜了空间 也会战胜时间
As it conquered space, it will conquer time.
你已经失去儿子了 琼斯博士
You've already lost your son, Dr. Jones.
你太太离开了
Your wife is gone.
难道还想失去干女儿
Do you really want to lose your godchild?
为了什么
For what?
这世界再也不在乎我们这种男人
A world that no longer cares about men like us.
谢谢
Thank you.
历史最伟大的一刻
History's greatest moment.
它的终结
Its end.
枪丢给我
Throw me the gun!
带他离开
Get him outta here.
泰迪
Teddy.
泰迪…
Teddy! Teddy!
快走
Come on! Go!
这边 快点
This way. Come on.
快走
Go!
印第
Indy!
快走
Go!
住手
Stop!
现在要怎样
Now what?
带他走
Bring him.
海伦娜 快点
Helena, come on!
- 泰迪 不能丢下他 - 不会
- Teddy, we can't just leave him. - We're not!
跟我走
Follow me!
快
Come on!
快点
Come on.
泰迪 快走 我们有车
Teddy. Come on. We've got a car.
可恶
Crap.
待在这
Stay there.
上车
Hop on.
第一个半球设定目的地
The first hemisphere sets the destination.
第二个以亚历山大座标
The second calculates the location of the fissure…
计算裂缝的位置
in Alexandrine coordinates.
叫梅斯纳把这转换成经纬度
Have Messner transpose this to longitude and latitude…
再把航点传给飞行员
and transmit way points to the pilots.
抄近路
Shortcut.
- 座标37.07 - 是谁
- You got coordinates for 37.07. - So, who is it?
丘吉尔
Churchill?
艾森豪
Ike?
你要杀谁才能赢得战争
Who are you gonna kill to win the war?
几分钟后 在阿基米德的加持下
In a few minutes, with the help of Archimedes…
我们将飞进暴风眼
we shall fly into the eye of this storm…
通过西西里领空
and cross into Sicilian airspace…
在1939年8月20日
on August 20th, 1939.
往北飞越盟国 油料足以飞到慕尼黑
We will head north over friendly skies with enough fuel to reach Munich.
我的猎物会等着我
My quarry will be waiting for me…
在摄政王街16号
at 16 Prinzregentenplatz…
准备升级他的V1火箭
for an update on his V-1 rocket.
哪有纳粹会杀元首的
What kind of Nazi kills the Führer?
相信胜利的那种 琼斯博士
The kind that believes in victory, Dr. Jones.
希特勒点燃可燃烧千年的火焰
Hitler lit a fire that could have burned 1, 000 years.
我看见每个错误
I saw every mistake.
每个过失
Every blunder.
我会拨乱反正
And I will correct them all.
历史就是一长串失败 琼斯博士
History is a long list of losses, Dr. Jones.
问题就在谁犯错
It's just a question of whose.
停
Stop!
泰迪
Teddy.
你会开那种飞机吗
You think you can fly one of those?
北方运输机
A Nord?
没问题
Sure.
你好像不太确定
It's not a ringing response.
我没开过北方飞机
Well, I haven't flown a Nord.
你什么飞机都没开过
You've never flown any plane.
我去发动它
I'll get it started.
不要 泰迪
No, Teddy.
完蛋
Crap.
系好安全带 琼斯博士
Fasten your seat belt, Dr. Jones.
可能会有乱流
There might be some turbulence.
你是德国人 佛勒
You're German, Voller.
没必要搞笑
Don't try and be funny.
加油 吹牛大王
Come on, big talker.
好
Okay.
Okay. Okay.
数据正常 马力满档
Gauges green. Power full.
时速达到85英里就仰转
And when I reach 85, I rotate.
放下襟翼
Okay, wings down.
好 时速84英里
Okay, 84 miles an hour.
仰转
Rotate.
抵达目的地时间
Time to destination?
60秒
60 seconds.
大陆漂移
Continental drift.
Continental drift!
阿基米德不懂大陆漂移
Archimedes didn't know about continental drift.
不可能
He couldn't have!
当时还没人观察到
It hadn't been observed yet.
你偏离目标了
You're off target.
你座标所根据的地点
Your coordinates are based on markers…
已经移动了两千年
that have been moving for 2000 years!
你可能偏离10度
You could be off by 10 degrees, by…
30秒
30 seconds.
佛勒先生
Herr Voller…
你算错了
Your calculations are wrong!
- 佛勒先生 - 可以闭嘴吗
- Herr Voller… - Will you shut up?
我在思考
I'm thinking!
20秒
20 seconds.
维持航线
Hold the flight path!
15秒
15 seconds.
我不知道我们要去哪 尤根
I don't know where we're going, Jürgen.
10秒
10 seconds.
9秒
9!
但现在绝对…
But it sure as hell…
8秒
8!
7秒
7!
不是1939年
…ain't 1939!
6秒
6!
调头
Turn around!
中止
Abort!
调头
Turn around!
中止
ABORT!!!
我们被拉进去了
We're being pulled in!
你在干嘛
What are you doing?!
这是我的飞机
This is my plane!
你在开我的飞机
You're flying my plane!
我们死定了
We're going to DIE!!!
赶快拉升
We need to pull up!
重启引擎
Restart engines!
那是西西里
That's Sicily.
1939年
1939.
我成功了
I did it.
我成功了 琼斯博士
I did it, Dr. Jones!
前往慕尼黑
Setting coordinates for Munich.
昨天属于我们 琼斯博士
Yesterday belongs to us, Dr. Jones.
那些是罗马三列桨座战船
Those are Roman triremes.
继续飞
Keep it in the air!
主人
Master…
罗马人接近了
The Romans are getting closer.
他们有飞龙
They have dragons!
太惊人了
Amazing.
开门
Open the door!
你们做什么
What are you doing?
你们干嘛 白痴
What are you doing, you idiots?
他们以为我们是怪兽
They think we're a monster!
你得调头
You have to turn around.
这是叙拉古围城
This is the Siege of Syracuse.
公元前214年
214 BC.
你进入错误的战场
You got the wrong war.
主人
Master…
别出去 主人
Don't ride out there, Master!
飞龙
The dragons!!
我们得射下他们的飞龙
We must take down their dragons!
老大
Boss!
改变航线
Change course!
入口几分钟后就关闭
The portal closes in minutes!
我得回去
I have to go back!
我不能留在这里
I can't be here!
I CAN'T STAY HERE!!
飞机赶不过去的
The plane won't make it!!
让开
Get out of the way!
怎么样 野蛮人
How do you like that, you savages?
抱歉 老兄 你是纳粹
Sorry, pal, but you're a Nazi!
你怎么在这里
What are you doing here?
我来救你
Rescuing you!
把他打下去
Get him off!
印第
Indy!
降落伞
Parachute!
我有降落伞
I got a parachute!
抓好
Hang on!
放手
Let go!
降落伞给我
Give me the parachute!
抓住 抓好
Grab it. Hang on!
印第
Indy!
我们开始下坠了
We're losing altitude!
往下掉了
We're going down!
我控制不住了
I've lost control!
那些是我的朋友
Hey, those are my friends.
那些是我的朋友 我们得救他们
Those are my friends. We need to help them!
那些是我的朋友
Those are my friends!
找到了
Eureka.
他想降落
He's trying to land.
起来 印第 帮帮我
Come on, Indy. Help me.
起来 对
Get up. Yeah.
带你离开这里
We need to get you out of here. Okay.
帮个忙 坐起来
Help me. Sit up, okay?
起来 你得帮我
Sit up. You need to help me.
我知道很痛 但我得带你回去
I know it hurts, but we gotta get you back.
太不可思议了 袋熊
This is incredible, Wombat.
不可思议
Incredible.
对 真的
Yeah, it very well is.
我得带你离开
But we have to get you out of here.
天啊
My God.
我们见证了历史
We're witnessing history.
翻转这些数字
Reverse these numbers.
它们会带你回家
They'll get you home.
什么
What?
我要留下来
I'm going to stay.
不行 你乱讲
No. You're not serious.
你是认真的
Wow, you are serious.
印第 你中弹了
Indy, you've been shot.
你在流血
You're bleeding.
你不能待在这里
You can't stay here.
可以
Yes, I can.
为了什么
But for what?
用膏药和水蛭 慢慢痛死吗
For a long, painful death with poultice and leeches?
我想象过这种情况 袋熊
I've imagined this, Wombat.
我研究过
Studied it.
- 研究了一辈子 - 是
- All my life. - Yeah.
但如果留下 你会把它毁于一旦
And if you stay here, you will muck it all up.
而且会没命
And die.
求求你 起来
Please, get up.
海伦娜
Helena!
我成功了
I did it!
太赞了 泰迪 为你欢呼
Bravo, Teddy! Three cheers!
印第 该走了 起来
Okay. Indy, we've gotta go. Get up.
- 我带你上飞机 - 不要
- I need to get you into that plane, okay? - No.
- 非去不可 - 不要
- We need to. - No.
起来 你可以…我们可以
Get up. You can… We can!
主人
Master!
我们该离开了 主人
We have to leave, Master.
是他
It's him.
他问我们穿越了多久
He's asking how far we've come.
两千年
Two thousand years.
我们…
We've come…
穿越了两千年
two thousand years.
但我们没料到会遇见…
But we didn't expect to meet…
伟大的…
the great…
阿基米德
Archimedes.
你…
You…
本来…
were always…
就会…
going to…
见到我
meet me.
那个轮盘就像道具扑克牌
That dial is a forced deck.
只能带我们来这里
It doesn't take us anywhere but here.
他是做来求助的
He built it to get help.
我们刚吓跑了整批罗马海军
Well, we just scared off the entire Roman Navy…
我们帮得够多了
so I think we've helped enough.
抱歉 阿基米德
Apologies, Archimedes.
我是你的粉丝
I'm a fan…
但我们该走了 他受伤了
but we need to leave. He's hurt.
海伦娜
Helena…
轮盘不能让他留着
He can't keep that, by the way.
他必须自己做一个
He needs to build his own one.
海伦娜 我们该走了
Helena, we need to go!
印第 窗口快关闭了
Indy, the window is closing!
我们不能困在这里
We cannot get stuck here!
我想…
I want…
留下来
to stay…
陪你
with you.
不行…别答应
No, no, no! Do not say yes!
你很杰出
You are a brilliant man…
你是智者
a wise man…
天才
a genius…
海伦娜
Helena…
人民心中的英雄
a hero to your people.
但他帮不了你
But he can't help you.
这是你的时代
This is your time.
他得回到自己的时代
He must be in his own time.
他必须回去
He needs to be in his.
他的工作还没结束
His work is not done.
他必须回家
He needs to go home.
家里有药
There is medicine at home.
他不能死在这里 不能
He cannot die here. He can't.
海伦娜 上飞机吧
Helena, get on the plane.
我没事
I'll be all right.
才怪
No, you won't.
我需要这么做
I need to do this.
我也是
Me too.
早
Good morning.
肩膀还好吗
How's the shoulder?
比我的下巴好
Better than my jaw.
对
Right.
你该让我留下的
You should've let me stay.
没办法
I couldn't do that.
为什么
Why not?
首先 你会改变历史进程
Well, for starters, you'd have changed the course of history.
那是坏事吗
That's supposed to be a bad thing?
你本来就该在这里 印第
You're meant to be here, Indy.
这里
Here.
为了谁
For who?
玛莉安
Marion.
嗨
Hey.
泰迪
Teddy.
玛莉安
Marion.
你在做什么
What are you doing?
把买来的东西放好
Putting groceries away.
这里一点吃的都没有
There wasn't a scrap of food in this place.
不 说真的
No. Really.
有人告诉我你回来了
Someone told me you were back.
你回来了吗 印第
Are you back, Indy?
那是炸药
It was explosives…
印第在跑 玛莉安也在跑
and Indy was running, Marion was running…
接着飞机突然爆炸
and suddenly the plane exploded.
印第 你醒了
Indy, you're up and about.
对
Yes, I am.
Yes.
小朋友 我们去吃冰淇淋吧
Why don't we go and get some ice cream, kids?
玛莉安刚刚有买
But Marion just bought some.
我知道一个更棒的地方
Oh, I know a better place.
冰淇淋不嫌多 对吧
You can never have too much ice cream, can you?
回头见
See you later.
英国水手志向远大
A British tar is a soaring soul.
如山鸟般自由
As free as a mountain bird.
他强有力的拳头
His energetic fist.
应该准备抵抗…
Should be ready to resist…
看来好严重
That looks bad.
会痛吗
Does it hurt?
从头痛到脚
Everything hurts.
我知道这种感觉
I know how that feels.
有哪里不痛
Well, where doesn't it hurt?
这里
Here.
这里不痛
It doesn't hurt here.
还有这里
And here.
贾巴利 艾莉亚 慢一点
Jabari, Alia, slow down!
海伦娜 快点
Helena! Hurry up!
我尖叫 你尖叫
I scream, you scream…
大家慢一点
Everybody, slow down.
- 我尖叫 你尖叫 - 我尖叫…
- I scream, you scream - I scream, I scream.
我们都为冰淇淋尖叫
We all scream for ice cream!
慢一点
Slow down.